Guide to the Berkshire Forum Records TAM.146
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Berkshire Forum Records
1973-1990
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Berkshire Forum
Tauber, Kurt
TAM.146
14.5 Linear Feet in 14 record cartons and 1 manuscript box.
286 audiocassettes
The Berkshire Forum (1973-1990) in Stephentown, NY was an independent left venue that held workshops for discussion of social and political issues. The collection contains files on programs held at the Forum, files on tours sponsored by the Forum, administrative files, photographs, and audio.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Kurt P. Tauber, Chair of the Board of Directors of the Berkshire Forum, in 1991. Seven videos were donated by Betty and Herman Liverlight in 1992. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1950.212, 1991.004, 1991.007, NPA.1991.014, and NPA.1992.011.
Arrangement
Materials in Series I: Records, Series III: Audio Recordings, and Series IV: Videos are unprocessed. Series II: Photographs is arranged alphabetically.
Files are arranged in three series:
Missing Title
Series I: Records.
Series II: Photographs
Series III: Audio Recordings.
Series IV: Videos.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Berkshire Forum was an independent left venue where small groups met to discuss social and political issues. Guests stayed on the property and attended workshops on topics including United States social and political problems, international affairs, peace movements, and Communist countries. The Forum also held a radical writers retreat and sponsored tours to Cuba, the German Democratic Republic, Nicaragua, and the Soviet Union. Events were attended by both "old" and "new" leftists. Speakers included prominent activists and academics.
Herman (1912-2001) and Betty Liveright (1913-2008) founded the Forum in 1973 and headed it until 1989. The Liverights were lifelong social activists and had joined the Communist Party the year they married in 1936, but left in the mid-1950s. Herman Liveright refused to testify before Congress in a McCarthy-era investigation and was convicted of contempt of Congress; this was later overturned by the Supreme Court.
Related Archival Materials
What's Left: Dialectable Recipes from the Berkshire Forum (PAM 7735) in the library's pamphlet collection.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains files on the numerous workshops and other programs held at the Forum, whose topics included United States political and social problems, international affairs, peace movements, the Communist countries, and a radical writers retreat, administrative files (including board minutes) and files on tours sponsored by the Forum (including trips to Cuba, the German Democratic Republic, Nicaragua, and the Soviet Union). The collection also includes over a thousand photographs originating from seven photograph albums. Images mostly date from the 1980s and are mostly from Forum events, on grounds of the Forum, and from Forum tours. Additionally, the collection contains audio and video recordings of workshops.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact [repository contact information] with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Europe |x Tours.; Cuba |x Tours.; Stephentown (N.Y.); Audiocassettes.; Mailing lists.; Correspondence.; Press releases.; Socialism; Photograph albums.; Forums (Discussion and debate) |z New York (State) |z Stephentown.; Communism.; Communist countries -- Tours.; Workshops (Adult education) |z New York (State) |z Stephentown.; Central America |x Tours.; Liveright, Herman; Berkshire Forum; Liveright, Betty; Tauber, Kurt
- Series I: Records
  - Board minutes, 1990; Cuba tours, 1980-1982; Finished workshops, Abrash-Bloch, 1981-1990., 1981-1992 (Box 1)
  - Finished workshops, Oke-Sweezy, 1978-1989; Workshop attendance books, 1973-1979, 1973-1989 (Box 2)
  - Communist Parties workshop, 1990; Florida reunion, 1985-1986; Marge Greavett correspondence, 1987-1990; Video workshops, 1987; Workshop arranging, 1980s, Workshop attendance books, registration, 1980-1990; Workshop ideas, 1985-1986, 1985-1990 (Box 3)
  - Brochures, 1979-1986; Puerto Rico tour, 1982; Radical writers retreat, 1984-1990; Rentals (by other orgs.), 1975-1990, 1974-1990 (Box 4)
  - Cuba tours, 1983-1990; Housekeeping (cookbook, graphics); Press clippings, 1973-1975., 1973-1990 (Box 5)
  - Movie forum, 1986-1990; "Plaudits"; Press clippings, 1977-1990; Special workshops, including: Industrial crisis, Labor, Peace, Church, 1985-1988 (Box 6)
  - Board Minutes, 1990; Board committees, including Property, Program, Finance, Staff, late 1980s; Committee of Consultants minutes, 1974-1989; Lease & Bylaws; Finished workshops, Bates-Byrd, 1975-1978., 1974-1990 (Box 7)
  - Finished workshops, Cameron-Cox, 1982-1990; Tours: Grenada, German Democratic Republic, Israel, Italy, Nicaragua, Soviet Union, 1981-1989, 1981-1990 (Box 8)
  - Finished workshops, Craig-Kwong, 1975-1990 (Box 9)
  - Finished workshops, Laibman-Nolan, 1976-1989; Finished workshops, Tanglewood-Zipser, 1983-1990; Administrative, 1989-1990; Daily World advertising correspondence, 1970s-1980s; Fundraising, 1970s-1990; Guest book, 1981-1990; Mailing lists, 1989-1990; Press releases, 1978-1990; Schedules, 1970s-1990, 1976-1990 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence and Flyer, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Graphic, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 006, Folder 5)
  - Brochures, guestbook, fundraising records, 1980-1990 (Box 11)
- Series II: Photographs, circa 1983-1990
  - 10th Anniversary Album (I), 1983-1984 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - 10th Anniversary Album (II), 1983-1984 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Berkshire Forum 10th Anniversary, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - The Berkshire Forum Presents Album, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Nicaragua Cuba et al Album (I), 1988 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Nicaragua Cuba et al Album (I), 1988 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - PDW Staff Photo from Berkshire Forum, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Photograph Album #1 (I), undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Photograph Album #1 (II), undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Photograph Album #2, 1989-1990 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Photograph Album #3 (I), undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Photograph Album #3 (II), undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Series III: Audio Recordings, circa 1986-1990 (Box 12, Box 13, Box 14)
  Scope and Content Note
  Series III: Audio Recordings contains approximately 250 audiocassettes, mostly recordings of workshops dating from 1986-1990. Speakers and topics represented include Bettina Aptheker, political prisoners, Rainbow Coalition, Labor/Peace/Church, Milton Terris, Gus Hall, corporate capitalism, Central America, and Germany. Also includes cassettes for one board meeting in August 1990. Most cassettes are labeled. There are also some tapes not produced by the Berkshire Forum, including two cassettes of music made by Tom Juravich.
- Series IV: Videos, 1985-1989 (Box 15)
  Series IV: Videos contains seven videotapes depicting workshops that took place at the Berkshire Forum in the late 1980s.